This Episode is sponsored by
本期視頻由
Skillshare
Skillshare贊助播出
"But when two hares running side by side" "How can you tell the female from male"
“兩兔傍地走” “安能辨我是雄雌”
It's nearly impossible for me to express
花木蘭對我
Just how important the character of Mulan is to me
以及對中國文化的重要性
And to every single Chinese person
實在難以解釋
The Ballad of Mulan is taught in elementary school
《木蘭辭》是內地義務教育的重點課文
It's one of my favorite poem from China
也是我最喜歡的一首詩詞
And at one point in time
曾幾何時
I could recite the entire poem by heart
《木蘭辭》，我能倒背如流
There are opera plays
花木蘭的戲曲
There are TV shows
花木蘭的電視劇
Countless books for children and adults
花木蘭的連環畫
I can't think of any other traditional characters
沒有多少傳統人物
Who is this ubiquitous within a culture
能在一民族文化裏占有如此重要地位
It was the 90s
九十年代
Mainland China started importing Disney animated films
中國內地開始進口迪士尼動畫片
Not long after I watched the Lion King
《獅子王》上映完
I heard stories of Disney making a Mulan film
迪斯尼要制作《花木蘭》的消息傳開了
Chinese animation was pretty much in the gutter back then
當時，中國動畫坑坑窪窪
I was excited to see Mulan as a cartoon character
有機會看到花木蘭的動畫，我甚是興奮
Spring of 1999
1999年，春
Our elementary school trip brought us to the local cinema
小學郊遊，我們去了電影院
To see Mulan
說要去看《花木蘭》
I figured it's probably just a 1960s adaptation or something
我以為只是六十年代的老戲曲
To my surprise
沒想到
A Disney logo appears on the big screen
大屏幕上出現了迪士尼的城堡
Every kid in the theatre gasped
劇院裏的每個孩子都吃了一驚
We were ecstatic
大家欣喜若狂
And it was every bit as beautiful as I have hoped
這部動畫，如想象中一樣美麗
It's not a perfect film
電影並不完美
It has some questionable racial depictions
電影的種族描繪有點過時
Although I guess the Huns aren't around anymore?
不過……現在也沒有匈奴族了吧（笑）
And I heard people say it's a watered-down version of the story
也有人說電影劇情沒有抓到木蘭從軍的精髓
Then again, Chinese people love to say that to everything
不過好像每部電影都有人這麽說
None of the matters
這些問題都不是問題
Because for the first time, I feel represented in a cartoon
重點是，我是第一次看到一部動畫電影
My culture, my favorite story, on the big screen
在大屏幕上展示了我的文化、我的故事
And I'm just a dude
我還只是個男的
I can't imagine how powerful it must have felt to a young girl
很難想象，這部電影對年輕女孩有多大的影響
Mulan is unlike any other Disney female lead at the time
花木蘭與大部分，乃至所有迪士尼女主角
Arguably, ever
都大有不同
She's not born royalty nor nobility
她不是王族，亦非是貴族
And does not marry into one either
也沒有嫁入豪門
She's a warrior
她是個戰士
With a kill count of thousands
沙場上殺敵千人
For a traditionally highly patriarchal country
在中國這樣的父權國家裏
Mulan is an important icon
花木蘭是一個重要的標志
Who not only gives girls in China an important representation
她不僅代表著中國女孩
But a sense of empowerment
更是激勵著中國女孩
When Mulan defeats Shan Yu atop the palace
當花木蘭擊敗反派
The entire theatre of children cheered
整個電影院的孩子都雀躍歡呼
Clearly, the film did something special
可見，這部電影對我們有多重要
Fast forward 20 years later
二十年後
A new, live-action Disney Mulan came out
真人版《花木蘭》問世
And it came at the perfect time
恰逢其時
Feminism is, once again, a hot topic in China
女權主義再度進入內地視野
News of domestic violence
家庭暴力
And gender discrimination came into focus more and more
性別歧視，越來越受到關注
Preference for sons over daughters is still a big issue
重男輕女仍是一個問題
Those were empowered by Mulan during their youth
年輕時就被花木蘭所啓發的女孩子
Are currently fighting for their equality
長大了，正在為平權而戰鬥
It is the perfect time for a new generation of Mulan
現在，中國需要新一代的花木蘭
To inspire people
來鼓舞人心
And you Fxxked it up!
然後你把它搞屎了！
To understand how the live-action Mulan fails
要了解真人《花木蘭》的失敗之處
We need to see where the 1998 Mulan succeeds
我們得先看看動畫《花木蘭》的成功之處
The story of Mulan is set in a nonspecific era in ancient China
《花木蘭》設定在架空中國古代
A time when the greatest honor a woman can bring
這個時代，女人想要光宗耀祖
Is to get married and bear children
唯一辦法就是結婚生子
Which Mulan is terrible at
然而，木蘭並不適合當新娘
"Put it out!
“滅火！“
Put it out!
“滅火！”
Put it out!!"
“滅火！！”
During this time, the Huns begin to attack China
這時，匈奴開始入侵中國
To counter the offensive, China conscripts one son from each family
為了反擊，中國開始招兵買馬
"The Fa family"
“花家”
"No!"
“啊！”
Having no sons in the house
家無男丁
Mulan's father is the only one who can go
木蘭的父親是唯一可以參軍的人
Too wrapped up in the social order
拘泥于封建思想
Mulan's father refuses to consider otherwise
花木蘭的父親願意送命
"I know my place!"
“老夫有自知之明！”
"It is time you learn yours"
“你也該管管自己了”
And with his age, he will surely die on the battlefield
年老體弱，父親必會戰死疆場
To save him, Mulan decides to dress up as a man
為了救他，木蘭決定女扮男裝
And join the army
代父從軍
Mulan's journey empowers women in two ways
花木蘭的故事，以兩種方式激勵女性
First, by showing her capability in holding her own against men
其一，木蘭能與男人抗衡
Mulan starts off as a total amateur
參軍之初，她只外行一個
But so does everyone else
不過，大家也都彼此彼此
We see this ragtag group of soldiers train
在軍隊訓練期間
And in any and all relevant aspect
我們能看到
Mulan can keep up with men
花木蘭和男人們不相伯仲
As the other soldiers grow
隨著士兵們的成長
So does she
木蘭亦有進步
Here, the film made a statement that
言下之意
Women, in any practical situation
女人，在實際情況下
Can be just as capable as any other man
能力不比男人差
Mulan learns to be masculine
花木蘭學會陽剛
"And this... represents Strength"
“這個……代表力量”
She is capable of harnessing strength and power
通過訓練，木蘭和男人一樣
Traits that, traditionally, are valued by men
有了陽剛之力
But what's more interesting, is the second way the film empowers women
不過，電影不只歌頌女性的陽剛
By empowering femininity
更歌頌了女性的陰柔之力
Now, this sounds strange because at first glance
乍看之下，這並不合理
Mulan isn't very feminine
花木蘭並不陰柔
she is a tomboy and a failed bride
她是個男人婆，當不了新娘
"You may look like a bride"
“你雖然看起來像個新娘”
"But you will never bring your family honor"
“可你永遠不會為你們家爭光“
But she's also not good at masculinity
但她一開始也不陽剛
Being extremely awkward at pretending to be a man
裝男人裝的像智障
That's because those are the extreme versions of gender expression
因為這些陰柔陽剛，都是極端例子
Femininity means submission
陰柔就得唯命是從
Masculinity means aggression
陽剛就得好勇鬥狠
In a sense, Mulan's journey is to embrace her own gender expression
花木蘭的陰柔陽剛，是她自己的真實表現
She succeeds in doing traditionally masculine tasks
在當兵這種傳統陽剛的事情上
By refusing to engage in hypermasculinity
花木蘭沒有把自己局限在陽剛的思維裏
Rejecting the values of brute strength
她不以蠻力應對
Instead, she's able to overcome her challenge by using clever solutions
她選擇以巧妙的手法
On multiple occasions
去解決問題
And her friends learn from her, too
她的戰友們亦從總學習
They start off as hyper angry hyper-masculine men
從軍當初，他們都是一群好勇鬥狠的家夥
But by the end, are willing to be in drag
電影最後，卻願意男扮女裝
To save the emperor
營救皇帝
We see both sides learn to embrace each other
可以看到，男女兩方有互相學習
Girls can be manly
女孩可以陽剛
And that men being girly, is not necessarily a bad thing
男人陰柔，亦不是壞事
There is strength on both sides
陰陽皆有其道
And there is strength in not limiting one with either extreme
不局限于一個極端，才是正道
Finally, it's important to realize the climax is her trying to save the emperor
值得一提，電影高潮一幕，木蘭的目標是救皇帝
And not China
不是救中國
It has probably an unintentional moral
無意之中，電影似乎在說
That Mulan's power, and by extension, a woman's power
木蘭的力量，也就是女人的力量
Is best used to uphold the patriarchy
說拿來維護父權社會用的
The storytellers at Disney probably took notice, too
迪士尼也可能注意到了這一點
And to avoid that connotation
為了避免這種解讀
The film cleverly suggests that
電影巧妙地暗示
Mulan doesn't save the emperor out of loyalty
木蘭救皇帝，並非出于忠心
She merely sees the emperor as a fellow human in need of help
皇帝，在她心裏，也不過是凡人一個
But more importantly
重點是
After the dust settles
電影最後
The emperor offers Mulan a position in his counsel
皇帝想讓木蘭入朝庭當官
"You can have his job"
“你可以做他那份工作”
Mulan declines
花木蘭禮拒
Rejecting the value in upholding the patriarchy
拒絕了維護父權的工作
She returns home, to the only patriarch she recognizes
她回到家，見到了自己唯一認同的父權人物
Her father
她的父親
She presents him the sword and a medal
她獻上敵人的寶劍，皇帝的獎牌
Bringing symbolic honors to her family
為花家爭了光
What does the father do
父親什麽反應呢？
He tosses everything aside and embraces his daughter
他把所有的“光榮”扔到一邊，抱著他的女兒
"The greatest gift and hornor"
“我這輩子最大的光榮”
"Is having you for a daughter"
“就是有你這個女兒”
Breaking the final patriarchal relationship
打破最後一道的父權關系
Their love is a human one
父女的愛，不再受束縛
Instead of a dragon
沒了木須龍
Mulan 2020 has a no name phoenix that does nothing
真人版《花木蘭》多了一只啥事沒有的鳳凰
And the CGI looks like utter crap
特效看起來垃圾的很
Maybe it wouldn't be a problem
我想，電影的特效師們
If the animators joined Skillshare
需要到Skillshare進修一下
Skillshare is an online learning community
在線學習社區Skillshare
With thousands of inspiring classes for amateurs and professionals alike
為業余愛好者和專業人士提供了數千個不同的課程
Classes include character animations
角色動畫
Compositing
圖像合成
Greenscreen
綠屏特效
Which this movie also needs some help with
這部電影還需要哪些幫助
All of them are available and easily accessible
哦對這電影的綠屏也渣的要死
Get started with this class by Remington Markham
我建議從Remington Markham的課程開始
To bring your illustartions to life with Blender 3D
學習使用Blender 3D，使您的畫像作品栩栩如生
The same 3D animation tool used by Hollywood professionals
Blender 3D，可是電影業內人士也會用到的專業軟件
Classes are concise, ad free and affordable
課程簡單，無廣告，且價格合理
Less than ten dollars a month with an annual subscription
一年訂閱，每月費用不到十美元
For a limited time
限時之內
You can use the link in my description
你可以用下方鏈接
To get a free trial of Skillshare Premium Membership
免費試用Skillshare高級會員
Explore your creativity
探索你的創造力
Hone your skill
磨練你的功夫
Give Skillshare a try today!
馬上嘗試一下Skillshare吧！
Anyway, Mulan 2020 follows largely the same basic plot
好吧，真人版《花木蘭》的情節基本相同
Mulan fails to be a bride
花木蘭當不上新娘
China summons its troops
中國招兵買馬
Father too old to fight
父親年紀太大
Mulan leaves in her father's place
花木蘭代父從軍
But with a few critical differences
但劇情有幾點不同
Difference number one
差異其一
Mulan is now a naturally gifted fighter
木蘭變成了天資聰穎的神通
That is such an awful decision
這什麽垃圾設定
Instead of seeing Mulan growing alongside her friends
看不到花木蘭與戰友一同成長
Letting us know that women are as capable as men
看不到女人和男人不相伯仲
Now, only the select few who are blessed by the gods
現在，只有神童才有能力
Have the privilege of catching up with men
與男人並肩
Those who aren't so gifted?
沒有天資的人呢？
Like Mulan's unnecessary sister character?
看到木蘭的妹妹沒有？
Well, she gets married at the end of the film
嗯，她在電影最後結婚了
"I'm matched"
“我被許配了”
Imagine you are a young girl
想想你一下，你是個小女孩
With confidence issues
不是特別的自信
You watched Mulan 2020
您看了真人版《花木蘭》
Then you go back to school
然後回到學校
And see other girls who are prettier than you
看看其他女孩比你漂亮
Who are better at sports than you
比你跟擅長運動
Instead of saying you are just as capable with enough perseverance
動畫版木蘭說，只要努力，你也可以出人頭地
No, they are Mulan
不不不，真人版木蘭說
And you are just the sister now
你只是妹妹
Sorry, not everyone is special
有天資的人才是木蘭
Difference number two
差異其二
In the animation, Mulan is a problem solver
在動畫中，花木蘭善于解決問題
Mulan finds her way to the top using her wit
花木蘭不以蠻力
Instead brute strength
而以機智登頂
And, I have to emphasize this
而且，這點很重要
She's the ONLY ONE to make it
她是唯一一個能登頂的人
Mulan is able to solve this problem
花木蘭能解決登頂之難題
Because she can think outside the box
是因為她能打破框架
Without indulging in hypermasculinity
不沈迷于陽剛之思維
Where strength and brute force are valued
不著單純追求力量
In context, the hypermasculine ideal of strength
極端的陽剛之巅
Is and will always be only achievable by the few
只有少數人可以到達
Not everyone will make it
所以才說是“極端“
Mulan's success is a statement
花木蘭能登頂
That there is value outside of the hypermasculine way of thinking
說明解決問題的方式，不只有大男人的陽剛
The live-action version of this scene
真人版的這一幕
Has Mulan climbing the mountain with two buckets of water
花木蘭需要扛兩桶水爬上山頂
How does she solve this problem?
她有什麽巧妙方式嗎？
Mulan simply does the manly thing better than men
當然沒有，她直接就幹上去了
Through sheer strength and will power
力氣比男人大，意志力比男人強
To hammer this home further
這還不是一次兩次的事情
Mulan kills the villain by using his weapon
電影最後，木蘭以反派的大刀反殺
A weapon traditionally associated with men
大刀，傳統上說男人的武器
On the surface, it appears progressive
乍看之下，這似乎很有道理
That man and woman are not so different
男人和女人，沒什麽不同
But when carefully examined
但仔細一想就會發現
It is indulging in the traditional masculine value of strength
影片在歌頌傳統的男人陽剛價值觀
And that a woman is good
女人要登峰
Only if she can man up
就得跟男子漢一樣
Mulan's experience and perspective as a woman is not valued
花木蘭作為女人的經曆並不重要
If anything, her gender is a hindrance
甚至可以說，她的性別純粹說一個障礙
So instead of her teaching her friends to break free from hypermasculinity
和教誨大家打破規條的動畫版木蘭不同
She... just doesn't
真人版……什麽都沒教
The only lesson she learns in the film
她在電影中唯一表達出來的道理
Is to not hide her true identity
就是不掩飾自己的真實身份
And her naturally gifted power
不隱藏自己的天賦
"Then, you'll die pretending to be something you are not"
“到死了，你也只能假裝自己是男人”
Bitch! she has to hide her gender to save her family
艹尼馬！她隱藏身份是為了拯救家人
The two themes don't go well together!
這兩個主題從根本上就沖突了好嘛！
But what angers me the most
但是最讓我生氣的是
Is the third critical difference
第三個差異
The reason Mulan wants to save the Emperor
花木蘭拯救皇帝的動機
"I know my place"
“我有自知之明”
"And it is my duty"
“我的職責”
"To fight for the kingdom"
“是為國而戰”
"And protect the emperor"
“保護皇帝”
"I know my place"
“我有自知之明”
"It is time you learn yours"
“你也該管管自己了”
Look at her submissiveness standing next to the emperor
看看她在皇帝面前唯命是從的樣子
Her fight is literally to uphold the conservative hierarchy
辛辛苦苦，就是為了維持封建父權社會
Because in her story
大概她覺得
She's treated fine as a woman
她就算是女人
Or at least so she thinks
大家也待她不薄
"You'd believe Hua Jun"
“你會相信花軍的”
"Why do you not believe Hua Mulan"
“你為什麽不相信花木蘭”
This conservative value of "loyalty" and "honor"
這種“忠誠”和“榮譽”的價值觀
Is something that the people of China have abandoned and detest
在封建之末，民國之初
Ever since the collapse of the feudal system
便已被中國人所唾棄
We have a word for that!
這種思想，我們有個詞
"What is this fourth virtue I see?"
“這第四個美德是什麽呢？”
"Read it aloud, Mulan"
“朗讀出來吧，花木蘭”
"Devotion to family"
“孝”
It's called yū fǔ!
這叫迂腐！
Mulan doesn't challenge the status quo
花木蘭不僅不挑戰父權
"You can still take the noble path"
“現在走正道依然不遲”
She IS the status quo
她壓根就是父權代表
Perpetuating the notion that
象征著父權社會思想
Just because one supernaturally gifted woman is respected
僅僅因為天資聰穎的她受到社會尊重
Then all women are respected
就覺得所有的女人都可以贏得尊重
Gender equality achieved
覺得性別已經平等
Like the animated film
跟動畫裏一樣
Mulan returns home to meet her father
花木蘭回家見父
And that emotional moment
激動的一幕
Where the father abandons his symbol of honor, is gone
父親抛棄榮耀，沒了
Instead, their reunion is short and bland
他們的團聚變得短暫又平淡
That's because their reunion is not the final ending
畢竟，他們的團聚不是重點
Next, the emperor sends a gift to Mulan
重點來了，皇帝賜給木蘭寶劍一把
A sword, symbolic of her bringing honor to her family
象征著她為家人帶來的榮耀
This reward is played up much bigger
這份禮物的戲份，比父親重
Than her lesson about being who she is
比她學到的道理重
Or loving who she loves
比她愛的人都重
And once again, she's invited to work for the emperor
同樣，皇帝邀請她入朝當官
"To join our greatest decorated warriors"
“和我們最偉大的戰士們”
"As an officer and the emperor's guard"
“一同擔任皇帝的侍衛”
Does she accept the job?
她的反應？
The film ends before she gives an answer
她沒有回答，電影就結束了
But with her smile
但是看她的笑容
The answer is probably yes
答案估計是“遵命”
What a load of bullsh*t
尊尼麻痹
Now, the perceptive among you are probably already reading deep into this
心細的觀衆，恐怕已經深究了起來
And think there are all kinds of Chinese propaganda in this film
覺得這背後，怕有很多中國政治宣傳
Which, I don't really want to get into
這一點，我就不予評論了
Because I don't think that's the case
因為我覺得
That would be giving this movie too much credit
這電影應該不至于有政治宣傳
Mulan 2020 isn’t malicious, it’s just stupid
真人版《花木蘭》並無惡意，就是蠢
And it doesn't give a flying fxxk
而且一點進步的心都沒有
It only wants to appear diverse and inclusive
它只求表面上多元化
It has four writers
電影有四個劇作
Not one of them is Asian
沒有一個亞裔
Let alone Chinese
更不用說中國人了
Its dialogue sounds like a white person's oriental fetish
對白充滿了西方人對中國的臆想
"I told you you cannot eat, it'll ruin your make up!"
“我說了不能吃，會毀掉妝容的！”
"The fiercest winter storm cannot destroy this make up"
“就是寒冬最凜冽的風暴也不能毀掉這妝容”
It only wants to appear emotional
它只求表面上感人
Mulan fails to be a bride?
花木蘭當不了新娘？
No singing reflection
沒有唱歌
No contemplating her failure
沒有思考自己的失敗
No father-daughter bonding moment
沒有父女對話
The moment she steps out of the classroom
她從教室走出來
The minister is already there summoning the men to war
參謀就已經在村裏開始招兵了
When Mulan leaves
花木蘭離家從軍時
This is how Mulan's father reacts in the animation
動畫裏的父親說這個反應的
This is how Mulan's father reacts in live-action
真人版的父親則是這個鳥樣的
It only wants to appear empowering
它只求表面上激勵女性
Through the laziest ways
手法懶惰之極
Mulan is just naturally better than anyone
木蘭天生武功高強
Only some girls are special
只有天資聰穎的女孩子才有價值
The not-so-special girls should be happy
普通女孩子
Being fitted into traditional gender roles
救應該開開心心地
Get married and bear a child
結婚生子
"I'm matched!"
“我被許配了！”
And finally, it only wants to appear Chinese
還有，它只求表面上中國風
It makes no attempt at understand or deconstruct Chinese culture
它不了解，更不理解中國文化
It mixes up the Chinese Phoenix myth with the Egyptian myth
它把中國鳳凰和埃及鳳凰混為一談
"Some say the Phoenix is consumed by flame"
“有人說鳳凰會浴火重生”
It sings praises to a western understanding of Chinese conservative value
贊美著西方對中國封建思想的臆想
Failing to realize many of these values
根本沒發現，很多這些價值觀
Have since been abandoned by Chinese people
早被中國人所唾棄
It just wants to LOOK Chinese enough to fool the audience
它只追求有一個中國風的皮囊，騙騙觀衆
And the sad thing is
最可怕的是
It's probably going to work
很多觀衆依然會買賬
As I said, China needs Mulan right now
中國現在需要花木蘭
Instead, all we got is a big-budget virtue signaling
迪斯尼卻選擇拍個馬屁了事
Nothing signals that more than this moment
說到拍馬屁，最讓人惡心的就是這一幕
"Black wind and I rode along side two rabbits running side by side"
“我和黑風在外面看到兩只兔子在跑”
"I think one was a male, one was a female"
“我覺得應該說一雄一雌”
Mulan's dialogue here is a reference to the Ballad of Mulan
這台詞指的是《木蘭辭》的結尾
It takes one of the most iconic and powerful lines from the poem
中國最有名的詩篇之一，最經典的結句之一
And turns it into a throwaway fan service moment
變成了一句隨口台詞
In the Ballad
《木蘭辭》中
Mulan went to war for an astonishing ten years
花木蘭參軍十余年
And was promoted by twelve ranks
策勳十二轉
No one ever found out she was a woman
沒有一個人發現她是女人
She was that much of a badass
花木蘭是如此之厲害
In the poem, she also rejects a governing position
辭中，她也拒絕了當官
And chooses to return home
選擇回鄉
It was only when her fellow soldiers come to visit
知道她的戰友們前來拜訪
And see her, in a dress, wearing make-up
看到她衣著裙子，面帶妝容
Do they realize the truth
才明白真相
Confounded, they ask her why they never realized she's a girl
戰友不知所措：“十幾年來怎麽沒有人看出破綻？”
To which, Mulan replies
花木蘭答曰：
"The male hare’s feet go hop and skip"
“雄兔腳撲朔”
"The female hare’s eyes are muddled and fuddled"
“雌兔眼迷離”
"But when two hares running side by side"
“兩兔傍地走”
"How can you tell the female from male"
“安能辨我是雄雌”
Mulan's answer was poignant
木蘭之意，何其深遠
Men and women may look different
男女看似有別
But when living amongst each other
但彼此相處之時
When fighting beside each other
並肩作戰之時
What difference do the differences make?
男女之別，又有何別？